<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Gods handy-vvorke in vvonders Miraculously shewen vpon two women, lately deliuered of two monsters: with a most strange and terrible earth-quake, by which, fields and other grounds, were quite remoued to other places: the prodigious births, being at a place called Perre-farme, within a quarter of a mile of Feuersham in Kent, the 25. of Iuly last, being S. Iames his day. 1615.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1615</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 36 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A01791</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 11926</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S105736</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99841462</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99841462</idno>
            <idno type="VID">6047</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A01791)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 6047)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1067:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Gods handy-vvorke in vvonders Miraculously shewen vpon two women, lately deliuered of two monsters: with a most strange and terrible earth-quake, by which, fields and other grounds, were quite remoued to other places: the prodigious births, being at a place called Perre-farme, within a quarter of a mile of Feuersham in Kent, the 25. of Iuly last, being S. Iames his day. 1615.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[24] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by George Purslowe] for I. W[right],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1615.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The earthquake described occurred 1 March 1615 (o.s.) in Vaud canton, Switzerland.</note>
                  <note>With a title-page woodcut.</note>
                  <note>Printer's and publisher's names from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C⁴.</note>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Abnormalities, Human --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Vaud (Switzerland) --  History --  Earthquake, 1615.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:6047:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6047:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6047:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6047:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Gods Handy-vvorke in VVONDERS.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Miraculouſly ſhewen vpon two Women, lately deliuered of two</hi> Monſters: with a moſt ſtrange and terrible Earth-quake, by <hi>which, Fields and other grounds, were quite</hi> remoued to other places:</p>
            <p>The prodigious births, being at a place called <hi>Perre-farme,</hi> within a <hi>quarter of a mile of</hi> Feuerſham <hi>in</hi> Kent, <hi>the</hi> 25. <hi>of</hi> Iuly laſt, being S. <hi>Iames</hi> his day. 1615.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>two monstrous figures</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for I. W. 1615.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:6047:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6047:3"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Entle Reader, here is a liuely deſcription of the mercifulneſſe of our God, wherin thou mayeſt behold his Fatherly affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſhewed vnto vs Chriſtians, in that he forewarneth vs to flie from the wrath to come, as it appeareth by this picture here before thine eyes; the matter declareth vnto thee, the moſt horrible and ſtrangeſt birth of a child, that euer was heard or ſeene to bee borne of any Chriſtian woman in our dayes: which wonderfull ſtrange newes, God the Almighty doth ſend, to declare vnto vs his wrath, and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uy diſpleaſure to be at hand, except wee ſpeedily repent, and be heartily ſorrie for our former wicked life. But let our hope bee fully repoſed in the comfortable, and moſt ſweet promiſes of the holy Ghoſt, who pronounceth by the mouth of his ſeruants the Prophets and Apoſtles, theſe words to our comfort, At what time ſoeuer a ſinner repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth from the bottome of his heart, I will put all his wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe out of my remembrance, ſayth the Lord.</p>
            <p>Let not theſe fearefull and terrible examples terrifie or feare thee, gentle Reader; for all theſe things, as it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten <hi>Math.</hi> 24. muſt needes come to paſſe, but the end is not yet: For Nation ſhall riſe againſt Nation, and Realme againſt Realme, and there ſhall bee Famines, Peſtilences, Thunders, and Earth-quakes in all places, before the terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble day of the Lord do come, in which day all things, as it is written, 1. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5. That he ſhall come as a Theefe in the night: yet of his meere mercy doth hee vſe theſe terrible ſights as a meſſenger, and fore-teller of his wrath to come:
<pb facs="tcp:6047:4"/> For as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, When they ſhal ſay, Peace and ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, then ſodaine deſtruction commeth vpon them, as ſorrow vpon a woman with childe, and they ſhall not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcape in any wiſe. Therefore let vs not ſleepe in ſecurity, as others doe, but let vs watch and be ſober, for the day of the Lord is at hand, leſt ſodainly his wrath will come, and in the time of vengeance, he ſhall deſtroy vs: From the which, God the Father, for his Sonne Chriſts ſake, deliuer vs. AMEN.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:6047:4"/>
            <head>GODS WONDERS in Women.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F God had from the beginning of the world made all creatures beautifull, and in their perfect ſhape, his glory had not bin ſo great: but as white ſets off blacke, ſo theſe contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry colours in the creation of man, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times fayre, ſometimes deformed, expreſſe the ſkill, power, and omnipotency of the great Maſter, in whoſe hand it lyes to make a Begger, or a King, a beautifull body, or a monſtrous, and to faſhion thee or me as vgly, as that wretched ſhape (whatſoeuer it be) at which with wonder and loathing thou ſo often caſteſt an eye, haply of ſcorne.</p>
            <p>Neither are prodigious Birthes (for that is the wombe, which now is in labour) ſimple or meere miſtakings in God as if like a bungler in ſome common trade, he were not his Crafts-maſter: no, hee receiueth no leſſe honour from the ſhape of a Monſter, than from the rareſt piece of beautie, that euer was out of earth; no, we are all but one piece of clay, and as the Potter pleaſes, ſo are the veſſels made, ſome to baſe vſes, and others to noble: neither is the veſſell to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pine and aske the workman: Why didſt thou make me to no better purpoſe?</p>
            <p>Monſtrous births are Moales in nature, they are Wens ſticking on her cheeke to diſgrace her: they are to man and woman mockeries of their pride: for why ſhould either of them with <hi>Diues</hi> boaſt of their purple and rich cloathing, when an arme from heauen can ſtrike them, in a moment, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the leproſie of <hi>Lazarus?</hi> That face and forehead which
<pb facs="tcp:6047:5"/> thou painteſt for allurement, and ſo adorn'ſt it with iewels, to ſhew the glory of thy riches, is moulded out of the ſame fleſh and bloud, of which a begger is framed, and which gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth faſhion to a ſtigmatick, and miſhapen creature.</p>
            <p>To checke therfore our vicious condition, who are proud of that which muſt rot, and conſume with wormes bred out of our owne corruption: and to puniſh the ſinnes of ſome particular parents, God from time to time ſtriketh the womb of the mother, and doubleth his curſe, not onely in making her to bring forth with paine and dolour, but to bee deliuered with fearefull and horrid ſhapes, to aſtoniſh the beholders, and affright the ſinfull breeders.</p>
            <p>What man (vnleſſe the hammers of hell continually beat vpon his heart to harden it) being a father to a ſon or daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſo blaſted in the natiuity, but would at ſight of ſuch a hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror fall downe and die with ſorrow: or curſe himſelfe that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer his ſinnes were ſo blacke and monſtrous, as to moue the Almighty in his wrath to make his body, to be the begetter of an vgly Monſter? Say ſuch a childe ſhould liue to call him father, how vnpleaſing were the ſound? The very name of, <hi>This is my ſonne,</hi> ſhould preſently ſtrike him cold to the heart, with, <hi>This is my ſhame;</hi> or rather, <hi>This is my ſinne:</hi> For be aſſured, that albeit women with childe, may by blowes, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther miſfortunes miſcarry in their deliuery, and bring In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants into the world maymed in limbes, or deformed in coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, and this cannot chuſe but be an vnſpeakable griefe to the afflicted father and mother; yet when Gods owne fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers ſhall cruſh the loynes in the wombe, and ſet his markes of fearefull diuine vengeance, on the breſt of an vnborne Babe, to turne it into a Monſter, it is without all queſtion, a reuenge and puniſhment for ſome extraordinary ſinnes in the Parents. God neuer giues a ſound paiment but it is for a ſure fault: when an Infant is borne dumbe, deafe, or in a limbe miſhapen, he doth but ſhake the Rodde; but when the birth is prodigious and beyond Nature, the ſtripes are deep, for then he is angred indeede, and at euery ſuch blowe hee drawes bloud. Former ages hereof haue had plentifull de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrations:
<pb facs="tcp:6047:5"/> and theſe latter dayes of ours are too preg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant in the like examples.</p>
            <p>But omitting either of theſe, I beſéech you (Chriſtian Readers) to caſt your aſtoniſhed eyes vpon this late-begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Obiect of horror and miſery, lately ſent into the World, in <hi>Kent,</hi> in a place not far from <hi>Feuerſham.</hi> For at a Farme called <hi>Perre,</hi> ſtanding a quarter of a mile from the Towne before named, a poore wayfaring woman beeing great with Child, but not neere her time, ſeeing the night approaching, ſtept into an old Barne, there to take vp her lodging. Where it pleaſed God (for the puniſhment of hers and her huſbands ſinnes) before her expected hower, to ſtrike her with paynes, ſo that there ſhee fell in labour: And after many terrible throwes of terror and agonies, more then women commonly ſuffer in ſuch extremities, ſhée was after many tortures, and torments of Soule and body, deliuered of two Children: Twinnes they were, not of gladnes, but of ſhame and ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row; not of Motherly embracements, but of affrights and wonder. A brother and ſiſter they were, and yet I know not whether I may ſo tearme them: but if I could giue theſe names vnto them, yet neuer were Brother and Siſter ſo vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like to one another, or to thoſe that did beget them. For the one was a woman perfectly framed in all her limbes, ſauing that the body was pyned away, and by that meanes, meagre and leane. But the ſecond infortunate burden that came a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long with her, was neither a Brother nor a Siſter, but Both; for it was an <hi>Hermaphrodite,</hi> it was neither man nor woman, but ſuch as you might call both man and woman: yet inclining rather to the forme of woman than man, han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomely compoſed from the <hi>Nauill</hi> downewards, but a Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter vpwards, and below the knees: for one leg was greater than the other; and either foote had no more then fowre toes. Head it had none, nor necke, but in the breſt ſtucke out a bunched peece of deformed fleſh, which like a flap, beeing to bee lifted vp, it carried vnder-neath, the faſhion of a mouth with a tongue, and choppes, yet were they neither. Aboue this deformed mouth, grew forth a tuft of hayre, the bredth
<pb facs="tcp:6047:6"/> of a teſton, and more, and a full inch in bredth: out of the right ſide, came a thing like an arme, altogether formleſſe and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out bones, or the true ſhape of a hand, hauing two fingers onely, towards either ſide one. It had no pappes, but prints and markes like them in their places. The length of this diſproportioned creature was 13 inches, and in compaſſe 15 inches and a halfe. This was more fat and fleſhly than the former.</p>
            <p>The Father of theſe infortunate payre of Twinnes, na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med himſelfe <hi>Henrie Haydnot:</hi> the Mothers name was <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t,</hi> And being examined of their dwelling, they reported it had beene in <hi>Chelmesford</hi> in <hi>Eſſex.</hi> Theſe prodigious Births were ſent into the world on the 25. of Iuly now laſt (being Saint <hi>Iames</hi> his day) and were buried at <hi>Preſton</hi> a Towne neere <hi>Feuerſham:</hi> to behold whom, ſo long as their bodies reſted aboue earth, thouſands of people came from all places, the miſery of the ſad mother, béeing relieued by much money, which out of Chriſtian compaſſion, many beſtowed vpon her. GOD graunt that theſe and ſuch like other fearefull demonſtrations of Gods anger for our ſinnes, may call vs home to his fold, from whence worſe than monſters and wild beaſts we wander, to the euerlaſting ſlaughter of our Soules; from which the Lord of heauen deliuer vs. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Another ſtrange wonder at <hi>Arnheim,</hi> a towne in <hi>Gelderland</hi> the 23. of <hi>Ianuarie.</hi> 1615.</head>
               <p>THis vgly and fearefull Monſter was borne the xxiii. of Ianuarie, in the yeare of our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt, a Thouſand Sixe Hundred and Fiftéene, an enſample to vs of the great wrath of GOD, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of our manifold and great ſinnes, which now a dayes in euery place doth beare ſway, as Curſing, Swearing, Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheming of GOD, Whoredome, Drunkenneſſe, and the like, the which is truely to bee lamented. And euery man may let this fearefull Monſter or token of God, be vnto him a looking glaſſe, whereby to amend his life, and repent: for
<pb facs="tcp:6047:6"/> this birth was very wonderfull, and ſéene of many credible perſons that doe witneſſe hereunto, and hath been openly de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>clared, and publiſhed throughout the whole Towne of <hi>Arn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heim,</hi> and chaunced as hereafter followeth.</p>
               <p>A Citizens wife in the ſayd Towne, a comely woman (whoſe name for certaine cauſes I let paſſe) being great with Child, and looked euery day, her Husband (being one that had almoſt ſpent al his goods amongſt whores and theeues) did not leaue the fame, but without any regard of his Wife, or her time ſo neere, followed his naughtie accuſtomed vſe. For he was rather amongſt other naughty company, then in his houſe, or by his wife, which did not a little grieue his wife, who often rebuked him, both with good and bad wordes: all would not helpe, it made him to be more earneſt againſt her, and to vſe her ſo much the worſe, the which greeued her very ſore. She being now great with Child, (as aforeſayd,) vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a time her husband accompanied himſelfe againe with his companions and whores, yea in an open houſe, hee both druncke, daunced and leapt, both night and day, and thus v<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed all manner of filthie concupiſcence with them.</p>
               <p>This came to his wiues eare, whereupon ſhe hauing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligence thereof, was in a great chafe, ranne thither in a furie, told him his owne, and rebuked him for it, and ſayd: he ſhould ſome thing regard her great belly, and tarry at home, and leaue the companie of thoſe wicked women, for ſhee had but ſmall goodneſſe at his hands, and hath ſcarce to eate or drinke at home. Her Huſband little regarding her wordes, was in a raging anger, and would haue beate his wife: the company which were in the ſayd houſe, would not ſuffer him, and ſayd, he ſhould bethinke himſelfe better, be more wiſer, and not deale in ſuch ſorte with his Wife, ſeeing ſhee was great with Child, and looked euery day to be brought a bedde. Her huſband in his great anger, and vnaduiſedly made an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere: ſhe may beare the Deuill of hell. His wife on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide being ſore vexed, anſwered thereto, I would I might beare a Deuill, ſo ſhould I once be rid of this woe &amp; miſerie, wherewithall thou doſt ſo vex me, for thou wilt by no meanes
<pb facs="tcp:6047:7"/> leaue thy whore-hunting, but be alwaies in their companie, both drunken and halfe madde, the which I wofull woman muſt both heare and ſée.</p>
               <p>Thus in her anger ſhe returned home againe, and ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly after the time came: as ſoone as the neighbours and Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wife were come, ſhee began for very great paines to cry out fearefully, and not long after was brought a bed of this wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull Monſter, with ſo fearefull proportioned limmes: the which aſſoone as the woman was deliuered thereof, it ranne vnderneath the bedde. The proportion of his body and lims was as heereafter followeth, and was ſeene of many perſons, both men and women, which witneſſe the ſame openly.</p>
               <p>Firſt, this Child being a Monſter, was ouer his whole body very rough with hayre, and all blacke, except his belly which was like a Swanne.</p>
               <p>Secondly, the two feete vpon the which it did ſtand, were like to a Peacocks feete.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, his eyes were to behold, fearefull, for they ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned like fire, and were very great.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, he had a mouth like vnto a Storcke or Crane, altogether blacke and very fearefull to behold.</p>
               <p>Fiftly, it had a taile like vnto an Ore.</p>
               <p>Sixtly, it had two hornes vpon his head, which hung o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer him.</p>
               <p>Seuenthly, it had in ſteade of hands and fingers, clawes like vnto a fowle.</p>
               <p>In ſumme it was not found in any point like to a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an body: but was very fearefull and horrible to behold.</p>
               <p>After that it had now (with great trembling and feare) been ſeene of many men in the towne, and euery man aſtoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de thereat, in the end they ſmothered it betwixt two beds and ſo killed it.</p>
               <p>My brother in Chriſt, and Reader hereof, let not this which is here declared, ſeeme a fable vnto thee, for this and the like wonders, many haue been heard of heere and there, as Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters by Sea, ſignes in the Ayre, both of men and cattell.</p>
               <p>By this we do perceiue and marke, that the Lords com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming
<pb facs="tcp:6047:7"/> is at hand, and that ſhortly hereupon will follow the iudgement day, whereas we muſt not onely giue ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of our ſinnes, but alſo of all vaine works, words, and deedes. For now a dayes the common ſort of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple are wholy bent to wicked companie, whereas is curſing, ſwearing, eating, drinking, breaking of Wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>locke, and whoredome, like as was with this aforeſayd man of <hi>Arneheim:</hi> good people amend your ſinfull liues, and call to God for grace.</p>
               <p>Alſo this may be a looking glaſſe vnto euery wedded woman, whereby to refraine caſting out of ſuch vnad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſed words, like as did this aforeſayd wife, her time of deliuery being ſo neere, but rather to haue patience, by pacifying her wrath, and commit all matters to almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty GOD, that hee may amend all that, which in her husband is amiſſe, alſo to pray for him, that it wil pleaſe God ſo to turne his heart, that he may acknowledge his ſinnes, and ſo amend his ſinfull life. The almightie GOD, wonderfull in his creations, grant vs all his grace, that wee may amend our wicked liues, confeſſe his power, and haue euerlaſting life in Ieſus Chriſt our Lord. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:6047:8"/>
            <head>A TRVE DISCOVRSE OF THINGS happened by an Earthquake, the 1. of March 1615. according to the ancient ſupputation, in the <hi>pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces adioyning to the lake of</hi> Geneua, <hi>otherwiſe called</hi> Lacus Lemanus: <hi>and eſpecially in the villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges</hi> of hie Corberye, and Iuorne, which are periſhed.</head>
            <p>SYthence that GOD ſpeaketh vnto vs by all his workes, our duety is, not to paſſe ouer lightly that which he cauſeth vs to heare: but rather to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it ſo well and attentiuely, that the whole be refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to that end, vnto the which it appertaineth. He hath ſpoken vnto vs long time ſithence, by his holy word, publiſhed and preached in theſe latter dayes ſo faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that wée may ſay, that thoſe which haue liued before vs, doe followe vs in this, very farre off. But alas! the more he ſpeaketh, the leſſe we heare, and the hearts which ought to relent, doe ware the more hard; yea in ſteade of yeelding willingly vnto his obedience, there is ſuch a rebellion in the moſt part of men, that a great number of them make themſelues vtterly vnapt to learne.</p>
            <p>Neuertheleſſe, for all this hee ceaſeth not to ſet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore vs, that which is to the furtherance of our ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, aſwell by his promiſes (whoſe effects are felt and perceiued in the harts of thoſe, which loue him and feare him) as by his threatnings, by the which his will is, to
<pb facs="tcp:6047:8"/> terrifie the hypocrites contemners of his Maieſtie, the more to increaſe their condemnation. Indeede, if being admoniſhed, threatned and corrected, they ſhall perſeuer in their wickedneſſe, without doubt. God will continue his iuſtice, and diſplay his true and ſeuere iudgement in this world, to the continuance of it euerlaſtingly in the world to come. It is moſt certaine, that on what ſide ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer a man turneth himſelfe, he may perceiue the ſignes of the wrath of God, ingraued in al his creatures, whoſe age and wearineſſe in the ſeruice of men, in their corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, requireth nothing more then to be deliuered from the oppreſſion which they feele, through the wickedneſſe of ſuch as abuſe them, in diſhonouring God, and follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their wicked will.</p>
            <p>The heauens are witneſſe, the ayre, the water, and the earth cryeth nothing elſe. The plagues and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectiue diſeaſes, which haue almoſt vnpeopled the whole world, beare witneſſe hereof. The forren and ciuill warres which haue deſtroyed, and doe yet deſtroy the earth, doe declare it. The dearthes and famines which haue brought, and do bring to ruine many realms, doe ſhew the like. Neuertheleſſe they laugh, and mocke, no leſſe then in the dayes of <hi>Noe,</hi> whereas they ſhould ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther prepare the Arke to ſaue themſelues, when as the floud of the lake and eternall iudgement ſhall light vpon all creatures: for it ſeemeth to be euen already at hand. This Arke is vnfained repentance, which hauing the true feare of God for the foundation, cauſeth men to be grieued and ſorrowfull for their wickedneſſe paſt, with carefull and moſt earneſt ſtudie of well doing, for the time to come. To this repentance God doth call vs, by ſundry and diuers wayes, eſpecially by the ſignes afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolde by our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt, in the 24. Chap. of Saint <hi>Mathew,</hi> which ſignes in theſe later dayes, hee dayly ſetteth before vs as fore-runners of his glorious comming.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:6047:9"/>
            <p>Now our meaning is not, to ſpeake of things hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened far hence, or long ſithence, neither of impreſſions or ſights ſeene in the ayre within theſe few Moneths, ſuch as are burning flames, the Sun doubled, yea tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pled, or yet of thundring or lightning in the middeſt of winter: but onely of the Earth-quake happened the firſt of March, 1615. according to the ancient Almanack in the countreys of <hi>Lyonois, Maſconois, Daulphin, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoy, Piedmont, Valles, Swyſſe,</hi> and <hi>Burgonny.</hi> Nor yet to diſcourſe of the cauſes and effects thereof, as the naturall Philoſophers, according to their profeſſion, are wont to doe: but to warne euery one, that ſéeing the earth ſhaketh, we may take occaſion euery one of vs ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally, and particularly, to be affraide and quake in our hearts, conſidering the multitude of ſinnes, which ouerwhelme vs in this curſed time and extreme olde age of the world: And alſo that it is not here beneath that we muſt looke for our aſſurance, ſéeing that there is nothing firme or ſtable but aboue in heauen. For as Hiſtories witneſſe vnto vs, there haue ſeldome beene ſuch ſignes, but that there haue followed ſhortly after moſt great and cruell calamities, common and generall to all eſtates. And not to ſpeake of thinges befalne elſewhere, wee will briefely touch ſuch things as are chanſed in theſe quarters neere to the lake <hi>Lemanus,</hi> leauing vnto others, to doe the like of that which happe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to euery one in his Countrey.</p>
            <p>The 1. of March 1615. halfe an houre before 12. of the day, the skie being moſt cleare and faire, the Sunne ſhining, all ſodainely came the Earthquake, which laſted not aboue 10. or 11. minutes by the clocke, for that one time. It was eſpecially perceiued by the clic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keting of the windowes, and cracking of the houſes, ſhaking of trees, and ſtone walles, with a great noyſe and hollow ſound in the ayre.</p>
            <p>In many places there fell downe chimnies, the
<pb facs="tcp:6047:9"/> walles raſed and riuen, as amongſt the reſt at a towne called <hi>Bonne</hi> in <hi>Fuſſigny,</hi> at <hi>Thonon, Euyan, S. Mau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris</hi> in <hi>Chablage, Laufanne, Morges,</hi> and many other places.</p>
            <p>At <hi>Geneua</hi> fell downe thrée or foure chimnies, and a ſtone wall of an olde building, without any other ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary thing chauncing: ſuch is the ſingular proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of God. Although one hath moſt falſely publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed (at which hee may tremble and bluſh for ſhame, to haue lyed ſo manifeſtly in feigning) which hee hath written of the blackneſſe of the Lake, which he ſayth to haue beene the Satturday before: Item, of the walles and houſes <hi>du bour de four,</hi> and of the continuance of the Earthquake for the ſpace of two houres long, which was often renewed with whirle-windes. But to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne to our matter, not farre from thence there haue beene other accidents, no leſſe lamentable then memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable.</p>
            <p>For vpon Munday being the ſecond of March, the ſayd Earth-quake renewing his force in the places of the higher ſide of the Lake, and beeing redoubled the Tueſday following, bath at morning and at night, with winde and ſnowe, chanced that which followeth, in a place ſubiect to the Souereignity of <hi>Berne,</hi> diſtant from the ſaid ſide of the Lake two houres iourney, from a Towne called <hi>Aille,</hi> about foure gunne ſhottes: and this happened the Wedneſday following, being the fourth of March, betwixt nine and tenne of the clocke in the morning. A great quantitie of earth rowling (e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen as it were a huge ſtreame of raging water, falling from the toppe of a moſt high Rocke) from the tops of the Mountaines, glaunced a farre off, and as ſome ſay about one league, the which was not ſo much by the naturall motion, (which is from a high place vnto a lowe) as being driuen by windes and exhalations ming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led amongſt it.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:6047:10"/>
            <p>This earth was ſo driuen, that in one inſtant it co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered the places neere the valley, vpon the which it fell, and in carrying before it all the earth that it mette, the ſame was cleane taken away, the which was more eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly brought to paſſe, by reaſon that it was moued by the Earthquakes &amp; ſtirring winds, aſwell as the firſt earth which driued it: ſo that it chaunced in this, as commonly we ſee vpon the lake or tempeſtuous Sea, whereas one waue is violently driuen by an other. The diſcent &amp; val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley did not onely adioyne themſelues vnto it, but that which is moſt ſtrange, the little hilles vpon low places, and the valleyes were ſhaked likewiſe. Heere is fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thermore to be noted, that the place wher this remouing was, is right againſt a Cliffe cauſed by many hilles and hye places, that are commonly whereas the rockes of the hilles meete and touch together. Ouer againſt, in the yſſue of this Clyffe, was the higher ſide of Corbery, a little village or hamlet, containing about 8. houſes, 25. barnes, &amp; 3. water-milles. The earth fell from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue vpon the ſaid village ſo violently, that in a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment all was couered, one houſe excepted, whereas a thing moſt worthy to bee marked, chanced. The ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of the ſaid houſe, being aſtonied and amazed, through the exceeding great noyſe, which he heard, ſaid to his wife, he did verily beleeue the end of the world to bee come, and that it was neceſſary to pray to GOD to haue mercy on them. Whereupon without delay knee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling downe in their houſe, they perceiued ſuch fruit and profit of their prayers, that the earth which rowled as is aforeſayd, paſſed ouer their houſe in a manner as a huge waue, without any harme to the houſe, or any within it, ſauing that, the Maſter hauing his hat pear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, was hurt in the head. As concerning the other houſes and barnes, they were all throwne downe, and almoſt couered with earth. There chances alſo in the ſayd place, another thing not to bee omitted, that is to
<pb facs="tcp:6047:10"/> ſay, a child of a quarters age was found ſafe and aliue in the cradle (as he is yet, thanks be to GOD) hauing his mother found dead by him. The manner of it was this, the mother vpon the noiſe of the houſe falling, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king to ſaue her Child, claſped the cradle in her armes, wherewith all the houſe fell, and ſhe moſt pittifully bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, was found dead, the Child being aliue and ſafe, as is aforeſayd. The like befell to a maid child of a yeere old, which was found whole and aliue among the ruines of a houſe. As touching the water-milles, they were all broken, and in one of them happened another ſtrange thing: for being very low ſituated, the axeltree with the whéele, were found whole together in the top of a hill, which was higher then the ſayd Mill 500. paces or ſteppes. The number of men which periſhed in this Village 29. of Barnes 25. water-milles 2. of yeere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reuenues or Farmes within the towne, called in la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine, <hi>Praedia Vrbana</hi> 7. of Vines 23. acres: of tunnes of Wine 82. of Neate, Bullocks and Calues 81. of hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, mares and colts 16. of ſhéepe 73.</p>
            <p>The lower the earth diſcended, the more this mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happe increaſed: for falling vpon the next village, called <hi>Iuorn,</hi> which was lower, and at the foote of the hill, whereupon the ſayd <hi>Corbery</hi> ſtood, there periſhed of men 93. or a 100. perſons, (ſome affirme more) of houſes 62. barnes 101. fulling milles 3. of Vines 39. Acres: of Tuns of Wine 236. of Neate 166. of calues 112. Horſes and Mares 43. Shéepe 108. alſo great a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance of Corne, all kind of fodder for Cattell, with great quantity of houſhold ſtuffe: to bee briefe, this Village was well furniſhed with all kind of things, and was eſteemed one of the beſt in all theſe quarters.</p>
            <p>The ſituation of it was vpon a diſcent not ſtéepe, but ſlope and ſtretched out from the Eaſt to the Weſt. The ground was ſo fertill, that they receiued euery yéere 3. crops, as Wheat, Millet, &amp; Turnops. Furthermore, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt
<pb facs="tcp:6047:11"/> them were neither poore, nor begger, but eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one euen to the very leaſt, liued on their goods and labour, beeing a people very thriuing and painefull, voyd of all euill practices, as vſurie, contentions and ſuites, as all their neighbours doe witneſſe of them.</p>
            <p>It is ſaid alſo, that the aforeſaid falling of the earth, was ſo ſudden, that no pellet out of any gunne could be more ſwift, then all this ſaid remouing was paſt. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther report, that a farre off they beheld about 20. per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, the moſt being women, and children, which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming downe a hill to ſaue themſelues, were ouertaken, and ouerwhelmed with the ſayd falling of the earth.</p>
            <p>The moſt that periſhed were women and Children, by reaſon that moſt of the men were at labour in the fields. In this great affliction, GOD hath vſed ſuch mercy, that of euery houſhold, ſome were ſaued, either men or Children. Moreouer, beſides the moſt fearefull and terrible confuſion, which the falling of the earth cauſed, beeing mingled with great ſtones that mounted in the ayre, there was ſeene infinite ſparkles of fire, with a great and darke cloud, from the which did procéede a moſt ſtrong ſmell of Brimſtone.</p>
            <p>At the length the earth ſtaied it ſelfe, ioyning toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther 2. houſes, which are at this preſent time ſtanding whole, laden on one ſide with earth, to the halfe height of the walles, without any other hurt: beſides theſe, there remaineth yet 7. or 8. houſes, with as many barnes and other countrey houſes.</p>
            <p>The length of this diſcent is from the toppe of the mountaine, vnto the 2. ſayd houſes. The bredth is of 12. <hi>Arpantes,</hi> the depth is in ſome places leſſe then in ſome other: towards the ſide it is about two mens depth. It is a marueilous thing, that in all this diſcent ſo extended, whereas the houſes were, it is ſo plaine, that it ſeemeth as a portion of earth beene newly tilled and harrowed, without any appearance of the ruine of
<pb facs="tcp:6047:11"/> the ſayd houſes, no more then if there neuer had beene any: and that which is more, few or no ſtones are to be ſeene. From the place where the remouing tooke his beginning, vnto the 2. houſes, where it reſted, it is all as but one ruine, where there is but one houſe to bée ſéene.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Aille</hi> the middle roofe tiles of the Church fell downe, without that any other moued. Not farre from this place fell a rocke downe from a hill, the which was ſtayed in a cliffe of the ſaid hill, without any hurt. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny chimneis fell downe, many wals were riuen, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the reiteration of the earthquake, vpon ſundry daies. Hard by a place called <hi>Morteru,</hi> the Lake hath excéeded his ordinary bredth twenty paces, hauing ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried away a portion of a Vine-yard, the which they ſay was ſwallowed vp by opening of the earth.</p>
            <p>Some ſay, that at a Towne called <hi>Ville Neufue</hi> and in other places, adioyning vnto the ſame, the Earth-quake was ſo violent, that whole tunnes of wine were raiſed vpon their end. At <hi>Veuey</hi> many chimneis were caſt downe, many houſes looſened, and amongſt the vines <hi>de l'Auau,</hi> certaine walles were ouerthrowne. The Magiſtrates of <hi>Bearne,</hi> in whoſe ſoueraignty theſe ſayd things happened, haue appointed men, or officers to looke and prouide for thoſe men, that yet liuing haue loſt their friends and ſubſtance.</p>
            <p>Now let euery man iudge of theſe things, as the feare of God ſhall direct him. It is well knowne what the Philoſophers doe affirme to bee the cauſes of ſuch Earth-quakes; but if one doe weigh the diuerſity of their opinions, it will bée found that we muſt ſéeke hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er for the cauſes hereof, then in the ſtarres, fire, waters, vapours, exhalations and windes included in the bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els of the earth, to the which they cleaue full faſt: And that wée may come vnto the cauſe touched by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, In the 114. Pſalme, where hée ſayth: Before
<pb facs="tcp:6047:12"/> the face of the Almighty the earth leaped, as the ſcarred Rammes in the fieldes, and the hilles like trembling Lambes.</p>
            <p>Furthermore, to iudge of thoſe whom God hath ſo viſited, wée muſt remember, that it doth onely apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine vnto God, to whom the iudgement muſt bée left, without concluding, that thoſe of <hi>Iuorne</hi> were greater ſinners then we, according to that which our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt teacheth vs, in the thirtéenth Chapter of Saint <hi>Luke,</hi> ſpeaking of the <hi>Galileans,</hi> whoſe bloud <hi>Pilate</hi> had mingled with the ſacrifices, and of thoſe vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on whom. the Tower of <hi>Sylo</hi> fell: but wee muſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade our ſelues that except we do repent, we ſhal like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe periſh. God is not vniuſt, but contrariwiſe his workes are as a bottomleſſe pit, vnſearchable to men, into the which wée ought neuer to enter, but to ſtay our ſelues in worſhipping with reuerence his incompre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſible wiſedome. Surely, if we doe not condemne all thoſe, which were drowned by the waters of the floud; neither all thoſe which were deſtroyed by the fire falling vpon <hi>Sodome,</hi> and other places adioyning vnto it (for there were many children innocent in the tranſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the aged): farre leſſe ought wée to haue an euill ſuſpition of thoſe, which were not ſo giuen to ſinne as other men.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Laodicea, Coloſſi,</hi> and <hi>Hieropolis</hi> were ouerwhel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by an Earth-quake. In <hi>Aſia</hi> firſt fourtéene Cities, and ſithence twelue. In <hi>Thracia</hi> 11. and in <hi>Affrica</hi> one hundred haue béene deſtroyed by Earthquakes hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. <hi>Nicodemia, Antiochia, Alexandria, Conſtantino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> and other places infinite haue béene hazarded by Earthquakes. And who ſhal ſay, that ſo many condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned places as were then in the world, ſhould rather haue eſcaped; then the places aforenamed? Certainly, if God ſhould haue reſpect vnto the ſinnes of men, one vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage ſhould not haue felt his wrathfull hand: but all the
<pb facs="tcp:6047:12"/> world, eſpecially the great Cities, whereas the great and wicked ſinners bee, and the moſt fearefull ſinnes committed. But it pleaſed God, to beate the Dogge be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lyon, to puniſh the leaſt ſinners before the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt, to cut downe the naturall Olyue, before the wilde, and the greene wood before the ſeare.</p>
            <p>Let vs then wonder at the great patience of God, that beareth ſo much with this world, and let vs ſo ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of his iuſtice, that it be hereafter to haue recourſe to his mercie, the which I pray him, that he will vouchſafe to ſhewe vs, through Ieſus Chriſt, his onely Sonne, our Lord and Mediatour.</p>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>S. Auguſtine.</bibl>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Mieux vault le tremblement des humbles,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>que l'aſſeurance des Orgueilleux.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Better is the trembling of the lowly,</l>
                     <l>then the aſſurance of the proud.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
